[
  {
    "question": "If a matrix has $$13$$ elements, then the possible\r\ndimensions (orders) of the matrix are ",
    "questionType": "Single Choice",
    "difficulty": "Easy",
    "solution": "If order of matrix $A= a \\times b$<br/>Then number of element in $A = ab$<br/><br/>Given $ab=13$<br/><br/>So, $a=1, b=13$<br/><br/>or $b=1, a= 13$<br/><br/>So, $1\\times 13$ or $13 \\times 1$ are possible order of A.",
    "subject": "Maths",
    "chapter": "Matrices",
    "topic": "Introduction to Matrices"
  },
  {
    "question": "A matrix has $$16$$ elements Which of the following can be the order of the matrix?",
    "questionType": "Single Choice",
    "difficulty": "3",
    "solution": "A matrix of $ m $ rows and $ n $ columns has $ m \\times n $ elements. <br/><br/>On multiplying the rows and columns in the given options, we notice that all $ 1 \\times 16 = 16, 2 \\times 8 = 16, 4 \\times 4 = 16 $ ",
    "subject": "Maths",
    "chapter": "Matrices",
    "topic": "Introduction to Matrices"
  },
  {
    "question": "If $$A=\\displaystyle \\left[ \\begin{matrix} 1 &2 \\\\ 3& 4 \\end{matrix} \\right] $$, then which of the following is not an element of $$A$$?",
    "questionType": "Single Choice",
    "difficulty": "Easy",
    "solution": "$0$ is not present in given matrix.\r\nOption $A$ is correct.",
    "subject": "Maths",
    "chapter": "Matrices",
    "topic": "Introduction to Matrices"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the order of the matrix is $$1\\times2$$, then it is a ",
    "questionType": "Single Choice",
    "difficulty": "2",
    "solution": "Row Matrix is a matrix with only one row.<br/><br/>The dimension of a row matrix is given as $1 \\times n$ where $n$ is the number of columns.<br/>The order of the matrix is given $1\\times 2$<br/>So, it has one row and $2$ columns<br/>Therefore, it is a row matrix.<br/>Hence, option A is correct.",
    "subject": "Maths",
    "chapter": "Matrices",
    "topic": "Introduction to Matrices"
  },
  {
    "question": "If $$A=\\begin{bmatrix}1 & 1 &1 \\end{bmatrix}$$, then $$A$$ is a ",
    "questionType": "Single Choice",
    "difficulty": "2",
    "solution": "The given matrix $A=\\begin{bmatrix} 1 & 1 & 1 \\end{bmatrix}$, has only one row but multiple columns.<br/>So, $A$ is the row matrix.",
    "subject": "Maths",
    "chapter": "Matrices",
    "topic": "Introduction to Matrices"
  },
  {
    "question": "$$\\begin{bmatrix}\r\n 2  & 3   \\\\ \r\n 3  & 2       \r\n\\end{bmatrix}$$ is______________ matrix",
    "questionType": "Single Choice",
    "difficulty": "Medium",
    "solution": "A matrix $A=({A}_{ij})_{m\\times n}$ is said to be a square matrix when number of row elements is equal to number of column elements.<br/>So from given matrix, we have $m= 2, n = 2$<br/>Hence, given matrix is a square matrix.",
    "subject": "Maths",
    "chapter": "Matrices",
    "topic": "Introduction to Matrices"
  },
  {
    "question": "A matrix which is not a square matrix is called a _______ matrix.",
    "questionType": "Subjective",
    "difficulty": "Medium",
    "solution": "A matrix which is not a square matrix is called a $\\text{rectangular}$ matrix.<br/>For example, a rectangular matrix is $A=[a_{ij}]_{m\\times n}$, where $m\\neq n$",
    "subject": "Maths",
    "chapter": "Matrices",
    "topic": "Introduction to Matrices"
  },
  {
    "question": "$$\\begin{bmatrix}0 &0 & 0 \\end{bmatrix}$$ is an example of ",
    "questionType": "Single Choice",
    "difficulty": "2",
    "solution": "A matrix in which all the elements are equal to $0$ is called zero matrix or null matrix.<br/>$\\therefore $ $[ 0 \\space 0  \\space 0 ]$ is a null matrix.<br/>Option D is correct.",
    "subject": "Maths",
    "chapter": "Matrices",
    "topic": "Introduction to Matrices"
  },
  {
    "question": "If A and B are square matrices of order 'n' such that $$A^2-B^2=(A-B)(A+B)$$, then which of the following will be true?",
    "questionType": "Single Choice",
    "difficulty": "Medium",
    "solution": "R.H.S. $= (A - B)(A + B) = A(A + B) - B(A + B)$\r\n$= A^2 + AB - BA - B^2$\r\nThis will become equal to L.H.S. only when $AB = BA$ ",
    "subject": "Maths",
    "chapter": "Matrices",
    "topic": "Multiplication of Matrices"
  },
  {
    "question": "A square matrix $$(a_{ij})$$ in which $$a_{ij}=0$$ for $$i \\neq j$$ and $$a_{ij}= k (constant)$$ for $$i=j$$ is a",
    "questionType": "Single Choice",
    "difficulty": "Easy",
    "solution": "In the given matrix all the elements other than the diagonal are zero and diagonal elements are equal to K \"a \"diagonal matrix is a matrix in which the entries outside the main diagonal are all zero \"\r\nand \"A diagonal matrix with all its main diagonal entries equal is a scalar matrix\"",
    "subject": "Maths",
    "chapter": "Matrices",
    "topic": "Introduction to Matrices"
  },
  {
    "question": "Matrix subtraction is associative",
    "questionType": "True False",
    "difficulty": "3",
    "solution": "It is false.<br/>Because,<br/>for matrices $A,B,C$ of same order,<br/>$(A-B)-C\\neq A-(B-C)$<br/>$\\because A-(B-C)=A-B+C$ and <br/>$(A-B)-c=A-B-C$<br/>So, Matrix subtraction is not associative.",
    "subject": "Maths",
    "chapter": "Matrices",
    "topic": "Operations on Matrices"
  },
  {
    "question": "If $$ A\\quad =\\quad \\begin{bmatrix} 1 & 3 \\\\ 2 & 4 \\end{bmatrix},\\quad B\\quad =\\quad \\begin{bmatrix} 1 & 2 \\\\ 4 & 3 \\end{bmatrix}\\quad and\\quad C\\quad =\\quad \\begin{bmatrix} 4 & 3 \\\\ 1 & 2 \\end{bmatrix} $$ find\r\n$$ (AB) C $$",
    "questionType": "Subjective",
    "difficulty": "3",
    "solution": "$ (AB) $\r\n$ =\\begin{bmatrix} 1 & 3 \\\\ 2 & 4 \\end{bmatrix}\\begin{bmatrix} 1 & 2 \\\\ 4 & 3 \\end{bmatrix} $\r\n\r\n$=\\begin{bmatrix} 1+12 & 2+9 \\\\ 2+16 & 4+12 \\end{bmatrix} $\r\n\r\n$ =\\begin{bmatrix} 13 & 11 \\\\ 18 & 16 \\end{bmatrix} $\r\n\r\n$ (AB) C $\r\n$ = \\begin{bmatrix} 13 & 11 \\\\ 18 & 16 \\end{bmatrix}\\begin{bmatrix} 4 & 3 \\\\ 1 & 2 \\end{bmatrix}=\\begin{bmatrix} 52+11 & 39+22 \\\\ 72+16 & 54+32 \\end{bmatrix}=\\begin{bmatrix} 63 & 61 \\\\ 88 & 86 \\end{bmatrix}$",
    "subject": "Maths",
    "chapter": "Matrices",
    "topic": "Operations on Matrices"
  },
  {
    "question": "If $$\\begin{bmatrix} \\alpha  & \\beta  \\\\ \\gamma  & -\\alpha  \\end{bmatrix}$$ is to be the square root of a two -rowed unit matrix, then $$\\alpha,\\beta$$ and $$\\gamma$$ should satisfy the relation.",
    "questionType": "Single Choice",
    "difficulty": "3",
    "solution": "We are given a two-rowed unit matrix A, $A=\\begin{vmatrix} 1 & 0 \\\\ 0 & 1 \\end{vmatrix}$<br/><br/>Also given a matrix B such that $B=\\begin{vmatrix} \\alpha  & \\beta  \\\\ \\gamma  & -\\alpha  \\end{vmatrix}$ and $\\sqrt { A } =B\\Rightarrow A={ B }^{ 2 }$<br/>Now ${ B }^{ 2 }=\\begin{vmatrix} \\alpha  & \\beta  \\\\ \\gamma  & -\\alpha  \\end{vmatrix}\\begin{vmatrix} \\alpha  & \\beta  \\\\ \\gamma  & -\\alpha  \\end{vmatrix}=\\begin{vmatrix} { \\alpha  }^{ 2 }+\\beta \\gamma  & 0 \\\\ 0 & { \\alpha  }^{ 2 }+\\beta \\gamma  \\end{vmatrix}$<br/><br/>$\\therefore A={ B }^{ 2 }\\Rightarrow \\begin{vmatrix} 1 & 0 \\\\ 0 & 1 \\end{vmatrix}=\\begin{vmatrix} { \\alpha  }^{ 2 }+\\beta \\gamma  & 0 \\\\ 0 & { \\alpha  }^{ 2 }+\\beta \\gamma  \\end{vmatrix}$<br/><br/>Now by law of equality, ${ \\alpha  }^{ 2 }+\\beta \\gamma =1\\Rightarrow 1-{ \\alpha  }^{ 2 }-\\beta \\gamma =0$",
    "subject": "Maths",
    "chapter": "Number Systems",
    "topic": "Integers"
  },
  {
    "question": "Two matrices $$A$$ and $$B$$ are multiplied to get $$BA$$, if ",
    "questionType": "Single Choice",
    "difficulty": "Easy",
    "solution": "Two matrices $A$ and $B$ are multiplied to get $BA$, if number of rows of $A$ is equal to number of columns of $B$.",
    "subject": "Maths",
    "chapter": "Number Systems",
    "topic": "Integers"
  },
  {
    "question": "If $$A_\\alpha \\, = \\, \\begin{bmatrix}cos \\, \\, n\\alpha & \\sin \\, n\\alpha \\\\ -\\sin \\, n\\alpha  &\\cos \\, \\,  n\\alpha \\end{bmatrix}$$ , then the prove following .\r\n$$A_\\alpha\\,A_\\beta \\, = \\, A_{\\alpha + \\beta} \\, =\\,A_\\beta A_\\alpha $$",
    "questionType": "Subjective",
    "difficulty": "Medium",
    "solution": "$A_\\alpha\\,A_\\beta \\, = \\,\\begin{bmatrix}cos \\, \\alpha& sin \\,\\alpha\\\\ -sin \\, \\alpha  & cos \\, \\alpha \\end{bmatrix} \\begin{bmatrix}cos \\, \\beta& sin \\,\\beta\\\\ -sin \\, \\beta  & cos \\, \\beta \\end{bmatrix}$<br/>$= \\,\\begin{bmatrix}cos \\, (\\alpha + \\beta)& sin \\,(\\alpha + \\beta)\\\\ -sin \\, (\\alpha + \\beta)  & cos \\, (\\alpha + \\beta)\\end{bmatrix} \\, = \\, A_{\\alpha + \\beta}$<br/>Also $A_\\beta \\cdot A_\\alpha \\, = \\,  A_{\\alpha + \\beta}$ which can be shown  as above .    Hence proved .",
    "subject": "Maths",
    "chapter": "Matrices",
    "topic": "Multiplication of Matrices"
  },
  {
    "question": "If $$A$$ and $$B$$ are two square matrices of order $$n$$ and $$A$$ and $$B$$ commute then for any real number $$K$$, then",
    "questionType": "Single Choice",
    "difficulty": "Medium",
    "solution": "$AB = BA$    (GIven)<br/>Consider $(A-KI)(B-KI)$<br/>where, $K$ is any real number<br/>$(A-KI)(B-KI)= AB-K(A+B)+K^{2}$<br/>Interchanging $A$ and $B$, we get  <br/>$(B-KI)(A-KI)= BA-K(B+A)+K^{2}$<br/>Since $A,B$ commute with each other<br/>$\\therefore (B-KI)(A-KI)= BA-K(B+A)+K^{2} \\\\\\quad\\quad= AB - K(A+B) +K^2 = (A-KI)(B-KI)$<br/>Hence, option A is true and option C is false.<br/><br/>We cannot say anything about equality of $A-KI$ and $B-KI$, since it is not given that $A$ and $B$ are equal or not.<br/>Hence, option B is false.<br/> <br/>Consider $(A+KI)(B-KI)$<br/>$(A+KI)(B-KI) = AB - K(A-B) - K^2$<br/>Since $A,B$ commute with each other,<br/>$\\therefore (B-KI)(A+KI)= BA-K(B+A)+K^{2} = AB + K(A-B) +K^2 \\neq (A+KI)(B-KI)$<br/>It is proved that, $A+KI, B-KI$ do not commute with each other.<br/>Hence, option D is false.",
    "subject": "Maths",
    "chapter": "Matrices",
    "topic": "Multiplication of Matrices"
  },
  {
    "question": "If $$A$$ and $$B$$ are two matrices such that $$AB = B$$ and $$BA = A$$, then $$A^2+B^2$$ equals",
    "questionType": "Single Choice",
    "difficulty": "Easy",
    "solution": "Given, <br/>$AB = B$ <br/>and <br/>$BA=A$<br/>Now, <br/>$A^2+B^2=A\\cdot A+B\\cdot B$<br/>$=A(BA)+B(AB)=(AB)A+(BA)B$<br/>$=BA+AB=A+B$",
    "subject": "Maths",
    "chapter": "Number Systems",
    "topic": "Integers"
  },
  {
    "question": "If A is a square matrix of order 3,then $$|Adj\\left( Adj{ A }^{ 2 } \\right) |=$$\r\n",
    "questionType": "Single Choice",
    "difficulty": "3",
    "solution": "$|adj\\left( adj{ A }^{ 2 } \\right) |$\r\n$Q={ { |A }^{ 2 }| }^{ { \\left( 3-1 \\right)  }^{ 2 } }={ { |A }^{ 2 } }|^{ 4 }={ |A| }^{ 8 }$\r\n\r\n",
    "subject": "Maths",
    "chapter": "Number Systems",
    "topic": "Integers"
  },
  {
    "question": "The multiplication of matrices is distributive with respect to the matrix addition.\r\nState true or false.",
    "questionType": "True False",
    "difficulty": "Medium",
    "solution": "It is well known fact that, Multiplication of matrices is distributive with respect to the matrix addition. i.e $ A(B+C)=AB+AC$",
    "subject": "Maths",
    "chapter": "Matrices",
    "topic": "Multiplication of Matrices"
  },
  {
    "question": "The transpose of a rectangular matrix is a ",
    "questionType": "Single Choice",
    "difficulty": "Easy",
    "solution": "If we exchange the role of the  row and column of a matrix then we transpose it.This operation is called transposition and the matrix is called transposition matrix.<br/>If we take a rectangular matrix and transpose it then we get a rectangular matrix.",
    "subject": "Maths",
    "chapter": "Matrices",
    "topic": "Operations on Matrices"
  },
  {
    "question": "$$(A+AB)^{T}=XA^{T}$$,  $$\\mathrm{X}=$$",
    "questionType": "Single Choice",
    "difficulty": "3",
    "solution": "From equation <br/>$\\Rightarrow \\left ( A+AB \\right )^{T}$<br/>$\\Rightarrow A^{T}+B^{T}A^{T} $ $\\left \\{ We \\quad known \\quad that \\left ( AB \\right )^{T}=B^{T}A^{T} \\right \\}$<br/>$\\Rightarrow A^{T}\\left ( I+B^{T} \\right )$<br/>$\\Rightarrow A^{T}X$<br/>$\\therefore$ $ X= I$ $+$ $B^{T}$",
    "subject": "Maths",
    "chapter": "Matrices",
    "topic": "Operations on Matrices"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is not true, if $$\\mathrm{A}$$and $$\\mathrm{B}$$ are two matrices each of order $$n\\times n$$, then \r\n",
    "questionType": "Single Choice",
    "difficulty": "Medium",
    "solution": "By property of transpose of any matrix <br/>$\\left ( A+B \\right )^{T}=A^{T}+B^{T}=B^{T}+A^{T}$<br/>$\\left ( A-B \\right )^{T}=A^{T}-B^{T}$<br/>$\\left (  AB\\right )^{T}=B^{T}A^{T}$<br/>$\\left ( A B C  \\right )^{T}= C^{T} B^{T} A^{T}$\r",
    "subject": "Maths",
    "chapter": "Matrices",
    "topic": "Operations on Matrices"
  },
  {
    "question": "If $$A$$ is skew-symmetric matrix and $$n$$ is odd positive integer, then $$A^n$$ is",
    "questionType": "Single Choice",
    "difficulty": "Medium",
    "solution": "For a skew-symmetric matrix  A, $A^T=-A.$ <br/>$(A^n)^T= (-1)^nA^n$, since n is an odd integer then $A^n$ is also a skew-symmetric matrix. ",
    "subject": "Maths",
    "chapter": "Matrices",
    "topic": "Types of Matrices"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is the new row that results when you add rows $$1$$ and $$3$$?\r\r\n$$\\begin{bmatrix}3&4&2&11\\\\9&1&0&0\\\\0&1&0&2\\\\0&0&6&1\\end{bmatrix}$$",
    "questionType": "Single Choice",
    "difficulty": "Medium",
    "solution": "Given Matrix$=\\begin{bmatrix} 3 & 4 & 2 & 11 \\\\ 9 & 1 & 0 & 0 \\\\ 0 & 1 & 0 & 2 \\\\ 0 & 0 & 6 & 1 \\end{bmatrix}$<br/>Row $1=\\begin{bmatrix} 3 & 4 & 2 & 11 \\end{bmatrix}$<br/>Row $3=\\begin{bmatrix} 0 & 1 & 0 & 2 \\end{bmatrix}$<br/>Sum$=\\begin{bmatrix} 3+0 & 4+1 & 2+0 & 11+2 \\end{bmatrix}$<br/>$\\begin{bmatrix} 3 & 5 & 2 & 13 \\end{bmatrix}$<br/>$\\therefore $Option $2$ is correct",
    "subject": "Maths",
    "chapter": "Matrices",
    "topic": "Inverse of a Matrix"
  },
  {
    "question": "The value of $$\\left|\\begin{array}{ll}\r\r\n2+i & 2-i\\\\\r\r\n1+i & 1-i\r\r\n\\end{array}\\right|$$ is:",
    "questionType": "Single Choice",
    "difficulty": "Medium",
    "solution": "Let $A=\\begin{vmatrix}<br/>2+i & 2-i\\\\ <br/>1+i & 1-i<br/>\\end{vmatrix}$<br/>$det A=(2+i)(1-i)-(2-i)(1+i)$<br/>$=2-i+1-[2+i+1]$<br/>$=-2i$<br/>$\\Rightarrow det A= -2i\\Rightarrow A $ complex quantity.",
    "subject": "Maths",
    "chapter": "Determinants",
    "topic": "Introduction to Determinants"
  },
  {
    "question": "A determinant of second order is made with the elements 0 and 1. Find the number of determinants with non-negative values.",
    "questionType": "Single Choice",
    "difficulty": "3",
    "solution": "In required determinant , each of the four elements can be filled in $2$ ways i.e. by $0$ or $1$.<br/>So, possible number of determinants $= 2^4=16$",
    "subject": "Maths",
    "chapter": "Determinants",
    "topic": "Introduction to Determinants"
  },
  {
    "question": "If A is a square matrix of order n such that its elements are polynomials in x and its r-rows become identical for   $$x = \\alpha $$  then",
    "questionType": "Single Choice",
    "difficulty": "Medium",
    "solution": "Since $x-a$ will be common factor from each of r-rows which vanish by putting $x=\\alpha $,<br/><br/>Therefore ${ \\left( x-\\alpha  \\right)  }^{ r-1 }$ will be factor of $|A|$",
    "subject": "Maths",
    "chapter": "Determinants",
    "topic": "Introduction to Determinants"
  }
]